Modules are a super important part
of software development.
And so in this lecture,
we're gonna talk about modules in more depth
and learn how they work behind the scenes.
So essentially, a module
is a reusable piece of code
that encapsulates implementation details
of a certain part of our project.
Now that sounds a bit like a function
or even a class,
but the difference is that a module
is usually a standalone file.
Now that's not always the case,
but normally when we think of a module
we think of a separate file.
So of course a module always contains some code
but it can also have imports and exports.
So with exports, as the name says,
we can export values out of a module
for example, simple values or even entire functions.
And whatever we export from a module
is called the public API.
So this is just like classes
where we can also expose a public API
for other codes to consume.
Now, in the case of modules,
this public API is actually consumed
by importing values into a module.
So just like we can export values
in modules, we can usually also import values
from other modules.
And these other modules from which we import
are then called dependencies
of the importing module
because the code dead is in the module
dead is importing cannot work without the code,
that it is importing from the external module, right?
And this entire logic that I just described
is true for all modules
in all programming languages.
So this is not specific to only JavaScript.
In fact, modules are a pattern that developers
have been using in all languages for decades.
Now, of course we can write code without modules,
and actually we've been doing that
up until this point.
but that's because our applications
have been very simple.
However, when a code base grows bigger and bigger,
there start to be many advantages
of using modules.
And the first one is that modules make it
really easy to compose software.
So we can think of modules
as small building blocks
that we can then put together
in order to build really complex applications.
And I think it might be helpful
to look at a more real world example,
to understand all the benefits of modules.
So let's take this digital camera.
You can see that this specific camera
is basically made up of all these modules
that we can see here.
And this is exactly how we can compose software
using modules as well.
Another big advantage of these camera modules
is that each of them can be
developed in complete isolation.
So you can have one engineer working on the lens
and another one on the screen
and even another one on the controller module.
And the best part of this is that each engineer
can actually work on their own module
without even understanding
what the other engineers are doing.
And also without understanding
how the entire final camera works itself.
And so isolating components
is another huge advantage of using modules.
And again, isolating components
essentially means that each module
can be developed in isolation
without the developer having to think
about the entire code base.
He doesn't even need to understand all of it,
which makes it really easy
to collaborate on a larger team.
Next up modules make it very easy
to abstract or code.
And we already talked about
what abstraction means,
but basically we can use modules
to implement low level code
then other modules,
which don't really care
about these low level details
can import these abstractions and use them.
And back to our camera, the screen module,
for example, does not care
about the low level implementation details
of the controller module.
It can simply import the controller,
but without knowing how it works
and use it to control other parts of the camera.
And so that's essentially the power of abstraction.
Modules also naturally lead
to a more organized code base.
Because when we break up our code
into separate isolated and obstructed modules,
this will automatically organize our code
and make it easier to understand.
And so this alone is a huge benefit of modules.
Finally modules allow us to easily reuse
the same code in a project
and even across multiple projects.
For example, if we use the module
to implement a couple of mathematical functions
in a certain project,
and if we then need the same functions
in the next project,
all we need to do is to copy that module
to the new project.
And in our camera example here,
this company could now use the exact same lens
or the exact same screen
in different camera models,
all because they nicely abstracted these components
into self-contained reusable modules.
So this is how modules work
in software design in general.
But now let's take a look at modules
specifically in JavaScript.
So as of ES6,
JavaScript has a native built-in module system.
Now we did have modules before ES6,
but we had to implement them ourselves
or use external libraries.
So ES6 modules are modules
that are actually stored in files
and each file is one module.
So there is exactly one module per file.
But now you might be thinking,
well, scripts are usually also files, right?
And that's of course true.
And so let's not compare
these two types of files
in order to understand
that there are actually huge differences
between old school scripts and modern ES6 modules.
The first difference is that in modules,
all top level variables
are scooped to the module.
So basically variables are private
to the module by default.
And the only way an outside module can access
a value that's inside of a module
is by exporting that value.
So just as we learned in the last slide.
But if we don't export,
then no one from the outside can see the variable.
Now in scripts, on the other hand,
all top level variables
are always global and I showed you this
in the map d project, remember?
And this can lead to problems
like global namespace pollution,
where multiple scripts try to declare variables
with the same name and then
these variables collide.
So private variables
are the solution to this problem.
And that's why ES6 modules implemented it like this.
Next ES modules are always executed
in strict mode while scripts on the other hand
are executed in sloppy mode by default.
So with modules, there is no more need
to manually declare strict mode.
Also the disc keyword is always undefined
at the top level
while in scripts it points at the window object, right?
Now, as we learned in the last slide,
what's really special about modules
is that we can export and import values
between them using this ES6 import
and experts syntax.
In regular scripts,
importing and exporting values
is just completely impossible.
Now, there is something really important
to note about imports and exports,
which is the fact that they can only happen
at the top level.
So as you know, outside of any function
or any if block,
and we will see why that is in a second.
Also all imports are hoisted.
So no matter where in a code
you're importing values,
it's like the import statement
will be moved to the top of the file.
So in practice importing values
is always the first thing that happens in a module.
Now, in order to link a module to an HTML file,
we need to use the script tag with
the type attribute set to module,
instead of just a plain script tag.
And finally about downloading
the module files themselves.
This always automatically happens
in an asynchronous way.
And this is true for a module loaded
from HTML as well as for modules
that are loaded by importing
one module into another,
using the import syntax.
Now regular scripts on the other hand
are downloaded by default
in a blocking synchronous way,
unless we use the async
or differ attributes on the script tag.
So that's a great overview of ES6 modules,
but now let's dig a bit deeper
and really understand how modules
actually import other modules behind the scenes.
And to do that, let's analyze what happens
in this small code example.
So here we're importing a value
called rent from the math.js module
and show dies from the dumb.jsmodule.
Now, as always, when a piece of code is executed,
the first step is to parse that code.
Remember, so we talked about that way back.
But remember that parsing basically means
to just read the code,
but without executing it.
And this is the moment
in which imports are hoisted.
And in fact, the whole process of importing modules
happens before the code in the main module
is actually executed.
So in this example,
the index.js module imports,
the dumb and math modules
in a synchronous way.
What that means is that only after
all imported modules have been downloaded and executed,
the main index.js module
will finally be executed as well.
Now this is only possible
because of top level imports and exports
that's because if we only export and import values
outside of any code that needs to be executed,
then the engine can know
all the imports and exports during the parsing phase.
So while the code is still being read
before being executed.
Now, if we were allowed to import a module
inside of a function,
then that function would first
have to be executed before the import code happened.
And so in that case,
modules could not be imported in a synchronous way.
So the importing module
would have to be executed first.
But you might ask why do we actually want
modules to be loaded in a synchronous way?
Isn't synchronous bad?
Well, the answer is that this is the easiest way
in which we can do things
like bundling and dead code elimination.
So basically deleting code
that's actually not even necessary.
And trust me,
this is very important in large projects
with hundreds of modules
and that includes third party modules
from which we usually only want a small piece
and not the entire module.
So by knowing all dependencies
between modules before execution,
bundlers like webpack and Parcel
can then join multiple modules together
and eliminate that code.
And so essentially this is the reason why
we can only import and export
outside of any code that needs to be executed.
So like a function or an if block,
but now let's move on here.
So after the parsing process,
HIAS figured out which modules it needs to import,
then these modules are actually downloaded
from the server.
And remember downloading actually happens
in an asynchronous way.
It is only the importing operation itself
that happens synchronously.
Then after a module arrives,
it's also parsed and the modules exports
are linked to the imports in index.js.
So for example,
the math module exports a function called rent.
And this export is then connected
to the rent import in the index.js module.
And this connection is actually a life connection.
So exported values are not copied to imports.
Instead, the import is basically just a reference
to the export at value
like a pointer.
So when the value changes
in the exporting module,
then the same value also changes
in the importing module.
And this is quite important to understand
because it's unique to ES6 modules.
Other module systems do not work like this,
but JavaScript modules do.
And so you need to keep that in mind.
But anyway, next up,
to code in the imported modules is executed.
And with this the process of importing
modules is finally finished.
And so now, as I already said,
it's time for the importing module
to be finally executed as well.
So index.js in this example.
Alright. And by now you're probably tired
of listening to me.
And so let's quickly move on
and actually try all this with actual code.